听译、时间轴：刘巍然（学酥）
本节 我将要简单讨论
In this section, I will talk a bit more about
分布式系统与计算机网络之间的关系
the relationship between distributed systems and computer networking.
在分布式系统中 一般来说
So, in distributed systems, generally,
任意一个参与到系统中的计算设备都被称为一个节点
any computing device that is involved in the system we call a node.
节点可以是手机、笔记本、数据中心的服务器
So, a node could be a phone, or a laptop, or a server in a data center,
也可以是我们前面讲到的其他设备
or any of the other things we talked about earlier.
分布式系统的抽象通信模型是
And the fundamental communication abstraction of distributed systems is that
一个节点可以向另一个节点发送消息
one node can send a message to another node.
就这么简单 这就是分布式系统的全部基础了
That's it. That's the entire basis of distributed system.
一个节点可以向另一个节点发送消息
One node sends a message to another node.
这个抽象模型涵盖了所有可能出现的通信模式
And this captures all of the possible modes of communication that can happen.
当然了 实际中有很多不同类型的网络
Now, in practice, of course, there are lots of different types of networks
有很多从一个节点向另一个节点发送消息的方法
and different ways of getting a message from one node to another.
举例来说
So, examples of that would be,
如果你在大学里
if you're at the university,
你可能会使用大学提供的Wi-Fi 或者学院提供的Wi-Fi
you will be probably using university provided Wi-Fi or college provided Wi-Fi.
如果你在家 你可能会使用家里的网络连接
If you're at home, you probably have a home Internet connection.
如果你坐在咖啡厅 你可能会使用咖啡厅提供的Wi-Fi
If you're sitting in a coffee shop, you will probably be using the Wi-Fi there.
如果你出门在外
If you're out and about in town,
你可能会使用手机上的蜂窝数据通信网络
you will probably be using some cellular data on your phone.
这些只是你可以直接连接到的网络
And that's only the network that you connect to directly.
在这些网络之上 还有一个构成互联网基础的骨干网络
On top of those, there are the backbone networks in that form the Internet.
有很多不同类型的网络
And there are lots of different types of networks
不同类型的网络由各种不同的公司运营
operated by all sorts of different companies.
有些网络通过铜导线连接
Some of those go via copper cables.
有些网络通过光纤连接
Some of them are fiber optic cables.
有些网络通过海底光缆连接
Some of them go underneath the sea.
有些网络通过卫星连接 等等等等
Some of them go by a satellite, and so on.
有很多A向B发送消息的方法
All sorts of ways of getting messages from A to B.
进一步 也有很多不同的物理通信机制
In addition, they're all sorts of physical communication mechanisms
包括导线上的电子脉冲、无线电波、光纤电缆中的激光
such as electrical pulses on a wire, radio waves, or lasers going down fiber optic cables,
甚至可以是货车里的硬盘驱动器
or even hard drives in a van.
什么？货车里的硬盘驱动器？这根本不是网络连接！
What? Hard drives in a van? That's not a network connection!
我认为这也是A向B发送消息的一种机制
Well, I will argue this is also a mechanism from getting messages from A to B.
如果你持有海量的数据
So, if what you have is a very large amount of data
你想把这些数据发送给其他人
that you want to send to somebody else,
例如将数据发送给另一个数据中心
maybe to transfer it to a different data center,
直接通过互联网发送数据会非常慢、成本也非常高
then actually sending all of that data over the Internet can be kind of slow and expensive.
更可行的方法是 将所有的数据载入到一堆硬盘驱动器里
And it can actually make more sense to load all of the data onto a bunch of hard drives,
把硬盘驱动器盒子搬到货车上
load the box of hard drives into a van,
开着货车到达目的地
drive the van to the destination,
当货车到达目的地后
and when it gets to the destination,
你可以把硬盘驱动器中的所有数据下载下来
you can then download all of the data back off the hard drives,
把数据存储在需要存储的任意系统中
and store them in whatever system they need to be stored in.
人们实际中确实会使用这种通信机制
And people do this in practice actually.
以亚马逊网络服务为例 这是一个大型数据中心服务的提供商
And amazon web services, for example, which is a big provider of data center services,
他们就提供了这样的服务
they actually have this service,
你可以从他们手里租赁一个硬盘驱动器盒子
where you can rent a box of hard drives from them,
他们就会派一个员工把盒子发送给你
and it will come in a career service.
你可以把你所有的数据传到盒子里
And you can load all of your data onto it.
每个盒子大约可以存储50TB的数据
It takes about 50 terabytes or so on one of these boxes,
这样就可以发送数据了
and send it back.
当然了 这是一个非常慢的网络通信机制
And so, of course, this is a very slow form of networking,
因为可能需要花费一天或者数天的时间 数据才能到达目的地
because it might take a day or a couple of days for the data to arrive.
但这也是一个超高带宽的网络通信机制
But it is also quite a high bandwidth form of networking,
也就是说 你可以用这个机制传输海量的数据
that is, you can transfer large quantities of data.
我认为 站在分布式系统的角度看
And I would argue that from a distributed systems point of view,
这也是一种消息通信信道
this is just another messaging channel.
这是另一种从A向B发送消息的方法
It's another way of getting a message from A to B.
不同网络信道的区别在于信道的延迟和带宽不同
Distinction is just the latency and the bandwidth of those different networking channels.
不同网络的延迟差异巨大
So, latency varies hugely depending on what sort of network you're looking at.
举例来说 家中设备所使用的Wi-Fi
Within the devices on your home, Wi-Fi, for example,
或者相同数据中心内的服务器网络
or within servers in the same data center,
其网络时延大约为1ms 甚至可能小于1ms
you probably get like 1ms maybe less than 1ms
具体延迟取决于网络的拥挤和拥塞程度
depending on how congested the network is.
顺带一提 延迟指的是一个设备向另一个设备通信时所需的时间
Latency, that is the time that it takes to communicate from one device to another.
如果我们把实现转至互联网
If you're going over the Internet,
你希望与另一个大洲上的某个服务器通信
and you're talking to a server that is located on a different continent,
则延迟的量级大约为100毫秒
then it's probably more like on the order of 100ms.
当然了 货车硬盘驱动器的延迟大约为一天或者数天
Of course, hard drives in a van will probably take a day or a couple of days.
再次强调 这也属于一种网络信道
But still, it's just another networking channel.
带宽差异也是巨大的
In terms of bandwidth, this varies hugely,
如果信号比较好 手机3G网络带宽大约为1Mbit/s
Like a 3G phone might have like 1Mbit/s if you've got a good signal.
如果信号不好 带宽大约为100Kbit/s
It might be more like 100Kbit/s if you've got a poor signal.
家用频段的带宽大约为10Mbit/s
Home broadband might be like 10Mbit/s.
当然了 具体带宽数值和你与最临近网络提供商的距离相关
Of course, it varies very much how close you are to the next provider,
也和是否使用光纤等因素相关
whether you have fiber and so on.
我们可以大概估计出货车硬盘驱动器的带宽
Roughly estimating the bandwidth of hard drives in a van.
如果货车只运送一个硬盘驱动器盒子
Well, if you take one of these boxes,
则总时间约为数天 总时间包括：将所有数据载入到硬盘驱动器
and it takes a couple of days to do the whole loading data onto it,
把驱动器运送到另一个地点
getting it to the other place,
再把数据读取出来
getting the data back off it again,
你可以得出一个大概的估计值
you can probably estimate it
如果你只使用一个盒子 则总带宽约为1Gbit/s
at roughly being 1Gbit/s or something like that if you use one box.
当然 货车可以运送多个盒子 从而进一步提高带宽
Of course, you can send multiple boxes, in which case you can increase that number.
这是一个非常粗略的估计值
Those are just very rough numbers,
只是为了向大家感受一下
but just sort of to give you an idea of
各种不同网络相关参数的量级
the order of magnitude that we're talking about with these.
我现在会为大家展示一个分布式系统实例
So, I will now like to show you an example of one concrete distributed system
大家每天都会使用这个系统
which is a system that you use every day.
这个系统就是网页
And that system is the web.
我们可以站在分布式系统的视角对网页展开分析
And so, the web, we can now analyze through a distributed systems lens
来看看当你在网页浏览器中载入一个网站时 实际上都发生了什么事情
and see what actually happens when you load a website in a web browser.
具体来说 我们有两个通信实体
And so, what happens there is that we have two communicating entities.
首先 你有一个客户端
First of all, you've got the client,
客户端就是你电脑或手机上的网页浏览器
which is the web browser running on your computer or your phone.
你有一个坐落在某个数据中心内的服务器
And you've got the server, which is usually located somewhere in a data center.
当客户端希望展示一个网页页面时 客户端要构造一个请求
And when the client wants to display a web page, it makes a request.
请求就是要通过网络发送的一条消息
So, a request is just a message that gets sent over the network,
这条消息要发送给特定的服务器
and that request is targeted at a particular server.
请求包含客户端尝试载入的URL路径
And it contains the path of the URL that you're trying to load.
大家可以注意到 URL以HTTP开头 也可能以HTTPS开头 随后是两个斜杠
So, you notice, in the URL, you have the HTTP, maybe S, double slash,
接下来是服务器名称
then comes the server name,
然后是一个斜杠 后面跟着的是路径
and then from the single slash onwards is the path.
斜杠前面是服务器名称
And so, the bit before that first slash is the server name,
服务器名称就是客户端消息要发送到的目的地
which is going to be the destination where we sent the message to.
斜杠后面就是路径
And what follows after that is the path,
路径也会被包含在消息中 一起发送到目的地
which is then contained within the message that we send to that destination.
这就是请求消息
And so, that's message.
如果是载入一个网页页面 此请求就被称为GET请求 请求中包含路径
If you want to load a web page, we call that a GET request. And it contains the path.
服务端会响应请求 将网页页面返回给客户端
And the server then will respond with the contents of that web page.
如果是一个普通的静态网页 则服务端返回的就是一个html页面
And so, that is probably an html page if it's just a plain web page.
但返回的内容也可以是一个图像
But it could also be an image,
可以是一个视频文件
or it could be a video file,
可以是一个PDF文档 也可以是其他任何内容
or it could be a PDF document, or anything like that.
因此 我们这里给出的是一个包含两条消息的简单协议
And so, what we have here is a simple protocol consisting of two messages,
一条消息是客户端发送给服务端的请求
a request from the client to the server,
一条消息是服务端反馈给客户端的响应
and a response from the server back to the client
响应包含客户端请求的数据
containing the data that the client asked for.
我想做一个简单的演示 给大家展示一下这个协议具体是什么样子的
So, I'd like to now give you a little demo of what this actually looks like.
大家肯定知道网页浏览器是什么样子的
And so, of course you know what a web browser looks like.
我这里载入的是课程网站 我可以上下滑动
Here, I've loaded the course web page, and I can scroll up and down.
现在 我可以用一个网络捕获工具
And I can now record the messages
记录网络中发送和接收的消息
that are sent and received over the network using a network capture tool.
我们这里要用的工具叫Charles
So here, I'm going to use a tool that's called Charles.
我们把Charles设置为记录模式 工具就会开始记录了
And I'm going to put it into recording mode. It's going to start recording.
我们回到网页浏览器 点击刷新 重新载入网站
And then, I'm going to go here and just hit reload on the website.
好了 我们已经重新载入网页了
And so, here we go, we've loaded the page again.
现在 回到Charles
And now, go back to Charles.
可以看到 工具累积了一系列请求信息
And we can see that we've now accumulated a whole bunch of requests.
这里的每一行都是一个请求消息
So, each line here is one request message
都是网页浏览器向服务端发送的请求
that was made from the web browser to the server.
工具记录的内容还包含服务端返回给客户端的响应
And it also contains the response that was sent back from the server to the client.
举例来说 我们这里可以看到
And so, here we can see, for example,
第一个请求就是请求网页浏览器中输入的路径
the first request here was for this path here, which is the path on the web browser.
大家可以看到 URL与这里记录的路径是相同的
You can see here in the URL that matches up with this path.
大家可以看到 这是一个载入特定网站的GET请求
You can see it's a GET request to load a particular website.
大家可以看到一系列信息
You can see a bunch of information,
例如这里的用户代理（User Agent）
like the User Agent here, for example,
这实际上是我所使用网页浏览器的版本
is essentially the version of the web browser that I'm using.
标识了客户端的软件版本
So, it identifies the client software version.
这里的Accept报头指明了网页浏览器可以解读的文件类型
Here, this Accept header, this indicates what file types the web browser understands.
我的网页浏览器可以解读html文件、各种图像格式、还有其他很多文件
So, it understands html and various other image formats and stuff like that.
这里还包含了一系列信息
Then, there's a whole bunch of other stuff here,
例如网页浏览器可以接受的压缩格式 我所使用的语言 等等
like what sort of compression it accepts, what sort of language I speak, and so on.
报头包含了很多的信息
So, all sorts of stuff here.
大家可以在这个面板中看到请求消息
And what you see in this panel here is the request message.
在下方的面板中 大家可以看到响应消息
And then, in the lower panel here, you see the response message.
这里是上方请求消息所对应的响应消息
And here, the response message to this.
这里包含了一些html信息
Here contains some html.
大家可以看到整个html页面的内容
And you can see like the whole content of the html page.
我可以滚动浏览内容 这些信息有点无聊
I can scroll down. It's a bit boring.
我们也可以看看其他的请求
OK, and we can have a look at other requests here as well.
大家可以看这个请求 这是一个下载的图片
So, you can see this here. It's a picture that it's downloading, and etc.
这是一些css信息 一些样式文件 等等
Here's some css, some style files, and so on.
这里我们展示的是
So, what we have is
一个从概念层面看非常简单的请求应答消息协议
this very simple request response messaging protocol at the conceptual level.
从概念层面看 从分布式系统层面看
So, at the conceptual level here, at the distributed systems level,
这个协议只是发送了一条消息 得到了一条响应
we're just talking about one message, one response.
物理网络层发生的事情
Now, what happens at the underlying physical network level
相对会更加复杂一些
is a little bit more complicated.
我们可以通过使用另一个网络捕获工具
And so, we can look at what happens at the physical level
看看物理层发生了什么事情
by using a different network capture tool.
我们这里用到的工具叫Wireshark
So, I'm going to use a tool here that's called Wireshark.
这个工具捕获的不是HTTP层的信息
And this will actually capture rather than capturing at the HTTP level,
捕获的不是请求和响应
capturing the request and response,
这个工具捕获的是一个个独立的网络数据包
it's going to capture the individual network packets.
我们来看看具体发生了什么
So, let's see what happens here.
我们让工具开始记录 随后回到网页浏览器 重新载入网页
I'll start recording, and then I'll go back to the web browser, and I'll reload again,
我们回到工具页面 点击停止
and go back here, and hit stop.
我们这里可以看到 天哪 物理层有好多活动
And here, we now see, oh, a lot of activity again.
在Wireshark中 表格内的每一行都是一个单独的网络数据包
And so, here in Wireshark, every line in this table is a single network packet.
大家在这里可以看到
And so, here you can see that
这是从一个IP地址发送到另一个IP地址的一个数据包
there's a packet sent from one IP address to another IP address.
这里的192.168
So, the 192.168,
是我记录数据包所用笔记本的IP地址
that is the IP address of my laptop on which I'm recording this right now.
这个128.232就是服务端 这就是服务端的名称
This 128.232 etc., that is the server, that is the name of the web server
是我正在连接的计算机实验室网站的名称
that of the computer lab website that I'm connecting to.
大家可以看到 连接用的是TCP协议
And so, here you can see it's connecting using the TCP protocol.
不同过于担心
Don't worry too much about that.
大家会在计算机网络课程中学到很多有关TCP协议的知识
You'll learn a lot more about TCP in the computer networking course.
大家可以看到 TCP协议下面包含了好多往来的数据包
But the bottom line of this is there's a lot of back and forth, you can see.
这里出现了加密过程 因为这是一个HTTPS连接
And then, here, there's some encryption that happens because it's an HTTPS connection.
大家可以看到 这里是我正在连接的网站名称
And you can see that here's the name of the website that I'm connecting to,
这是我正在连接的服务器名称 等等
the server name that I'm connecting to, and so on.
在网络的物理层发生的事情是
And so, on the physical level, what's happening here on the network is that
所有这些数据包在相互发送和接收
we have all of these network packets going back and forth.
有这么多数据包的原因是
And the reason that we have lots of packets is that
每个数据包有一个大小上限
there's a maximum size of each packet.
大家可以在这一列看到每个数据包的字节长度
And you can see here in this column, it has the size the length in bytes of each packet.
大家可以看到 数据包最大也就到1500字节左右
And you can see that the length only goes up to about 1500 bytes.
这是另一个1500字节左右的数据包
Here another with 1500 bytes.
但没有任何数据包的大小超过1500字节
But there are none that are bigger than that.
这是因为网络数据包有一个大小上限
And that's because networks have this maximum size of a packet.
如果你想发送一条消息 消息长度超过了单一数据包大小的上界
And so, if you want to send a message that is greater than the size of a single packet,
你就必须把这条消息拆分为多个数据包
you have to split it up into multiple packets.
这就是TCP协议所完成的工作
And this is exactly what the TCP protocol does.
HTTP协议在TCP协议之上运行
So, the HTTP runs on top of TCP.
HTTP使用了请求/响应消息的范式
So, HTTP has this request message response message paradigm,
但一条消息的长度可能会大于单个网络数据包的长度
but a request might be bigger than a single network packet,
一条响应的长度很可能会大于单个网络数据包的长度
and a response is quite likely bigger than a single network packet as well.
HTTP下方使用了TCP
So, then, HTTP uses TCP underneath,
TCP将这些长消息拆分为小的网络数据包
and TCP breaks down these big messages into small network packets
每个网络数据包都变得足够小 使物理层可以传递这些数据包
that are small enough that the network can deliver them.
在接收方侧
And then, on the recipient side,
TCP把所有的网络数据包放在一起
TCP puts all of the network packets back together again
为上层组合出一个长字节序列
to give us one large chunk of bytes.
在分布式系统中 大家特别要记住的一点是
And so, this is now like an important thing to keep in mind in distributed systems
当讨论消息的发送和接收时
when we're talking about messages being sent and received,
我们讨论的不是单个数据包的发送和接收
we're not talking about individual packets,
因为消息大小可能比单一网络数据包的大小要大
because a message may well be bigger than a single network packet.
因此 需要把长消息拆分为小的网络数据包
And so, that message then has to be broken down into small network packets.
因此 两个节点间相互发送的消息
So, the message is really a higher-level conceptual object
是一个高层级的抽象概念
that gets sent back and forth between two nodes.
如何在数据包层拆分消息
And how exactly this gets broken down on the packet level,
是我们留给计算机网络相关人士的问题
that's something that we leave to the computer networking people.
在分布式系统层面
So, for distributed systems point of view,
我们可以直接做出假设
we can just assume that we have this mechanism
我们已经有了一个发送请求和接收响应的机制
through which we can send these requests and these responses here.
我们不需要特别关注
And we don't care too much about the details of
物理层面如何描述网络数据包的细节问题
how this is actually physically represented in terms of network packets.
我们只假设我们已经有了一个通信机制
We just assume that we have this communication mechanism.